Guide to the Martin Shubik Papers, 1938-2017 and undated RL.01181
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Writings, 1951-2016; undated; 1
  - Articles, Book Chapters, and Other Papers, 1951-2016; undated; 3
    - On Fiduciary Risk and Decision-making (typed manuscript with revisions), undated (Box 107)
    - On Local and Network Games with Quint, T., 2003 (Box 108)
    - On Matching Book: A Problem in Banking and Corporate Finance, 1992 (Box 128)
    - On Production and Growth, undated (Box 109)
    - On Sensitivity Analysis, Economic Models…, 1972 (Box 110)
    - On the Future Role of the Corporation, 2000 (Box 107)
    - On the Role of Numbers and Information in Competition, 1975 (Box 128)
    - On the Stages of Innovation, 1995 (Box 110)
    - On the Trail of a White Whale Part 2, undated (Box 125)
    - On the Trail of a White Whale: Part 2.5 - The Rationalizations of a Mathematical Institutional Economist and Gamer, 2016 (Box 128)
    - Open Questions in Defense Economics and Economic Warfare, 1990 (Box 128)
    - Organization and Concept of a Playable Game, 2005 (Box 128)
    - Oskar Morgenstern, undated (Box 109)
    - Paper by Thomas Quint and Martin Shubik, 1996 (Box 126)
    - Paper Gold, undated (Box 109)
    - Past, Present and Future of Experimental Gaming, 2000 (Box 128)
    - Phylax, 1988-1991 (Box 109)
    - Phylax issues and drafts, 1988-1991 (Box 124)
    - Please tax some of us more, 2011 (Box 126)
    - Price Strategy Oligopoly with Product Variation, 1969 (Box 128)
      Includes reprint and working paper
    - Production with Dividend and Bankruptcy Penalties with Sobel, Li, 1993 (Box 109)
    - Quantity Variation Oligopoly with Fouraker, L., Siegel, S., undated (Box 109)
    - RAND Corporation Reports with Dalkey, N. and Brewer, G., 1968-1971 (Box 109)
    - Rational or Irrational Threats, undated (Box 110)
    - Referee report: A stochastic, infinite-horizon economy with secured lending or unsecured lending and bankruptcy, 2000 (Box 126)
    - Referee report: A strategic market game with active bankruptcy, 1999 (Box 126)
    - Reflections on Career, undated (Box 128)
    - Reminiscences of John Nash, 2015 (Box 126)
    - Research notes, Simulation of Socio-Economic Systems, Ecuador, 1960s; 3 folders (Box 47)
      Includes drafts and research materials for project on simulation and games
    - Review: Financial control of a Competitive Economy without Randomness, 2010 (Box 126)
    - Risk Aversion, Fiduciary Relationships..., undated (Box 110)
    - Royalty statement, 1994 (Box 51)
      End "Restricted?"
    - Santa Fe Art Market: Dealer Dynamics, 1998 (Box 128)
      Includes abstract
    - Simple Agents and Increasingly Complex Tasks, 2009 (Box 128)
    - Simulation/Gaming for Management-Related Theory and Research: A 1976 U.S. Survey, undated (Box 125)
    - Sin, Short Selling, Taxes, Bubbles and the Price of Shares, 2005 (Box 128)
    - Some Dynamics of a Strategic Market Game with a Large Number of Agents, undated (Box 125)
    - Some Musings of Gaming and Simulation, 1993 (Box 110)
    - Some Unresolved Problems in Mathematical Economics…, undated (Box 110)
    - Spatial Competition and Price Formation, 2000 (Box 128)
    - Stochastic Infinite-Horizon Economy with Secured Lending, or Unsecured Lending and Bankruptcy, 1999 (Box 128)
    - Strategic Market Games and Market Mechanisms, undated (Box 110)
    - The Analysis of Nuclear Stability in a Multipolar World with Bracken, J. and Quint, T., 1993 (Box 106)
    - The Characteristic Function and Strategic Form of an Exchange Economy, undated (Box 125)
    - The Competitive Equilibrium of a Direct Market and Core with Shapley, L., undated (Box 107)
    - The Computation of Equilibria in Monetary Economies with Quint, T. and Rutherford, T., 1995 (Box 107)
    - The Defense Implications of the Recent and Future Changes in the World... with Slighton, R., 1997; 2 folders (Box 107)
    - The Demand for a New Consumer Durable: some models, undated (Box 107)
    - The Economics of Competitive Strategy (outline of chapters, unfinished, with Forman, L. and Naylor, T.) (Box 104)
    - The Limitations of one-Dimensional Index Measures, 1995 (Box 126)
    - The Literature of Gaming, Simulation, and Model Building, 1972 (Box 108)
    - The Marginal Value of a Player, undated (Box 108)
    - The Names of the Games with Powers, I. and Yeung, I., 1990 (Box 109)
    - The One Bid Bargain, undated (Box 109)
    - The Playing of a Simple Extensive Form Game, 1991 (Box 109)
    - The Present and Future of Game Theory, 2012 (Box 126)
    - The Price for the Widow's Cruise, undated (Box 109)
    - The Regulatory Implication of Equity Investment for Life Insurance Companies, undated (Box 126)
    - The Santa Fe Art Market, 1992 (Box 110)
    - The Social Function and Economic Future of the Art Museum with Baumol, W., 1986-1989 (Box 110)
    - The Theory of Money and Financial Institutions, 1993; 1998 (Box 126)
    - The Uses of Teaching Games in Game Theory Classes…, 2002 (Box 111)
    - The Value of Money and Network Constraint with Bak, P., undated (Box 111)
    - The Variation of Stock Prices with Bak, P., Maslov, S., Karatzas, I., Sudderth, W., and Geanakopolis, J., 1996 (Box 111)
    - The War Game (outline, out takes), undated; 2 folders (Box 104)
    - Theory of Bidding with Griesmer, J., Morrison, H., undated (Box 110)
    - Three Essays on Decentralized Trade comments by M. Shubik, undated (Box 110)
    - Three Minimal Market Institutions: Theory and Experimental Evidence, undated (Box 125)
    - Three Simple Experimental Games, 1992 (Box 110)
    - Towards an Economic Dynamics, undated (Box 110)
    - Towards an Economic Dynamics with Many Generations with Arthur, W., undated (Box 110)
    - Trade Using One Commodity as a Means of Payment, 1977 (Box 128)
    - Trip Reports, 1956-1959; 1965 (Box 126)
    - Uncertainty and an Optimal Bankruptcy Law, 1984 (Box 110)
    - Update of the Aggressive-Conservative Investor, 2005 (Box 111)
    - Varying the Money Supply (drafts, undated; 4 folders (Box 111)
    - Who Gets What, How?, 2005 (Box 111)
    - Worldwide Nuclear Coalition Games: A Valuation of Strategic Offensive and Defensive Forces, 1993 (Box 128)
  - Books, 1954-2015; undated; 4
    This subseries contains files for Shubik's books. Files include published books, draft copies, marked-up drafts for revision, correspondence with co-authors and publishers, and marketing materials.
    - A Game Theoretical Approach to Political Economy, undated (Box 73)
      Includes draft cover. Seems to have become Volume 2 of Game Theory in the Social Sciences.
    - A Survey of Models, Simulations and Games, undated; 4 folders (Box 91)
      Includes draft manuscript
    - Barley, Gold, or Fiat? A Pre-Theory of Money, 2012 (Box 128)
      Includes reviews and related correspondence
    - Barley, Gold, or Fiat? A Pure Theory of Money, 2009; 2 folders (Box 125)
    - Book reviews for Shubik's books, 1975-1993 (Box 103)
      Includes copies of reviews of Shubik's books
    - Essays in Mathematical Economics in Honor of Oskar Morgenstern (1967), 1967-1968 and undated, 1961-1965; 8 folders (Box 73)
    - Game Theory, 1963 (Box 73)
      Includes memorandum of proof sent
    - Game Theory, undated; 2 folders (Box 74)
      Includes manuscript proof
    - Game Theory and Related Approaches to Social Behavior, 1962-1964; undated; 5 folders (Box 74)
      Includes draft manuscript, galley proofs, and related correspondence
    - Game Theory and Related Approaches to Social Behavior, 1964; 3 folders, second copy of book (Box 75, Box 161)
      Includes reprint, advertisements, and reviews
    - Game Theory in the Social Sciences, Vols. 1 and 2, 1960-1974; 7 folders (Box 75)
      Includes outline, drafts, and related correspondence
    - Game Theory in the Social Sciences, Vols. 1 and 2, 1973; undated; 10 folders (Box 76)
      Includes drafts, revisions, references, and notes from editor
    - Game Theory in the Social Sciences, Vols. 1 and 2, 1977-1981; undated; 9 folders (Box 77)
      Includes drafts, notes, editor comments, and references
    - Game Theory in the Social Sciences, Vols. 1 and 2, undated; 17 folders (Box 78)
      Includes drafts and notes
    - Game Theory in the Social Sciences, Vols. 1 and 2, undated; 9 folders (Box 79)
      Includes drafts and editor's mark-ups
    - Game Theory in the Social Sciences, Vols. 1 and 2, 1982; undated; 7 folders (Box 80)
    - Game Theory in the Social Sciences, Vols. 1 and 2, 1984; 6 folders (Box 80-A)
      Includes galley proofs
    - Game Theory in the Social Sciences, Vols. 1 and 2, 1971 (Box 125)
      Includes draft chapter
    - Guidance of an Enterprise Economy, 2015; undated; 6 folders (Box 128)
      Includes drafts, reviewer comments, responses to reviews, and related correspondence
    - Market Structure and Behavior, 1974; undated; 8 folders (Box 81)
      Includes drafts
    - Market Structure and Behavior, undated; 8 folders (Box 82)
      Includes drafts and related correspondence
    - Market Structure and Behavior, 1978; undated; 9 folders (Box 83)
    - Market Structure and Behavior, 1980; undated; 5 folders (Box 84)
    - Market Structure and Behavior, 1980; undated; 13 folders (Box 85)
      Includes galley proofs, notes, correspondence, references, and permissions
    - Market Structure and Behavior, 1978; undated; 5 folders (Box 86)
      Includes draft manuscript and advertisement
    - Market Structure and Behavior, 1989 (Box 128)
      Includes draft chapters and related notes
    - Mathematics of Conflict, 1980s; s 1990; 3 folders (Box 86)
      Includes draft manuscript and royalties statement
    - Money and Financial Institutions, c. 1999 (Box 86)
      Includes draft book cover
    - Political Economy, Oligopoly and Experimental Games, 1999 (Box 128)
      Includes related correspondence and galley proofs of book cover
    - Political Economy, Oligopoly, and Experimental Games, c. 1998 (Box 87)
    - Readings in Game Theory, undated; 17 folders (Box 87)
      Includes draft chapters and related correspondence
    - Readings in Game Theory, 1970; undated; 4 folders (Box 88)
      Includes permissions and related correspondence
    - Risk, Organizations, and Society (1991), 1981-1989; 13 folders (Box 88)
      Includes draft chapters and references
    - Risk, Organizations, and Society (1991), 1987; undated; 7 folders (Box 89)
    - Risk, Organizations, and Society (1991), c. 1991; 9 folders (Box 90)
      Includes drafts and galley proofs
    - Strategic Market Games, 1998 (Box 128)
    - Strategy and Market Structure (1959), 1954-1958; undated; 7 folders (Box 90)
      Includes drafts, referee reports, and related correspondence
    - Strategy and Market Structure (1959), 1958-1960; 4 folders (Box 91)
      Includes copy of book, reviews, and permissions
    - Strategy and Market Structure, 1959 (Box 161)
    - The Aggressive Conservative Investor, 1979 (Box 161)
    - The Control of an Enterprise Economy, 2008-2015; 6 folders (Box 125)
    - The Theory of Money and Financial Institutions, 1993-2012; 2 folders (Box 128)
      Includes draft material and notes
    - The Theory of Money and Financial Institutions (1999), 1971-1992; undated; 12 folders (Box 92)
      Includes outlines, resources, proposal, and drafts
    - The Theory of Money and Financial Institutions (1999), 1976-1992; undated; 12 folders (Box 93)
      Includes draft chapters
    - The Theory of Money and Financial Institutions (1999), 1987-1990; undated; 6 folders (Box 94)
    - The Theory of Money and Financial Institutions (1999), 1987-1990; undated; 7 folders (Box 95)
    - The Theory of Money and Financial Institutions (1999), 1987-1993; undated; 13 folders (Box 96)
    - The Theory of Money and Financial Institutions (1999), 1991; 2000; undated; 11 folders (Box 97)
      Includes, drafts, revisions, and notes
    - The Theory of Money and Financial Institutions (1999), 1993; undated; 5 folders (Box 98)
      Includes draft manuscript and editor's mark-ups
    - The Theory of Money and Financial Institutions (1999), 1991-1997; undated; 6 folders (Box 99)
      Includes draft and copy for revisions
    - The Theory of Money and Financial Institutions (1999), 1993; undated; 4 folders (Box 100)
      Includes copy of manuscript and revised proof
    - The Theory of Money and Financial Institutions (1999), undated; 8 folders (Box 101)
      Includes revised proofs and copy of manuscript
    - The Theory of Money and Financial Institutions (1999), undated; 7 folders (Box 102)
      Includes copy of manuscript
    - The Theory of Money and Financial Institutions (1999), undated; 10 folders (Box 103)
      Includes revised proofs, reviews, and related correspondence
    - The Uses and Methods of Gaming, 1975 (Box 161)
    - Unfinished book by Shubik and Sabel, 1984; 3 folders (Box 123)
    - Who Gets What, How?, 2015 (Box 128)
  - Referee Reports, 1957-2002; 5
    Includes files for Shubik's referee activity for academic journals and publishers.
    - Referee file, 1973-1976 (Box 40)
    - Referee reports, 1972-1976; 5 folders (Box 40)
    - Referee reports, 1985-1986 (Box 49)
    - Referee reports, 1988-2000; 2 folders (Box 43)
    - Referee reports by M. Shubik, 1960-1963 (Box 47)
    - Referee reports by M. Shubik, 1968-1971 (Box 43)
    - Referee reports listing, 1959-1980 (Box 49)
    - Referee reports, by M. Shubik, 1957-1967 (Box 47)
    - Reviews and referee reports, 1980-1986 (Box 49)
    - Reviews and referees, 1999-2002 (Box 43)
    - Unidentified referee reports, 1966 (Box 47)
  - Unidentified Papers, 1963-1997; undated; 6
    This subseries includes draft papers by Shubik that do not have a clear connection to any of his published works.
    - A Static Theory of Cooperative or Collusive Action, undated (Box 106)
      Includes draft chapter 8 for unidentified work
    - Corporate Control, Efficient Markets... (working papers, correspondence), undated (Box 104)
      Includes working papers and related correspondence
    - Diagrams and figures from Volume II, undated (Box 104)
    - Drawings and manuscripts on game theory, undated (Box 105)
    - Entry and exit growth, undated (Box 104)
      Includes draft chapter 8, hand-written
    - Entry, Exit, and Growth, undated (Box 123)
      Includes chapter 8 of unknown work
    - Figures and tables for various publications, undated (Box 105)
    - Mathematical institutional economics and oligopoly theory, undated (Box 105)
      Includes draft chapter 13 of unidentified work
    - N-Person Games, 1963 (Box 105)
      Includes draft chapters for unidentified publication
    - Prices, Production, Advertising, and the Goals of the Firm, undated (Box 105)
      Includes draft chapter 6 for unidentified book
    - Probability/consumption models, undated (Box 105)
    - Secondary sources for "14" (includes articles by B. Shitovitz and others), undated (Box 105)
    - Secondary sources for "6.2.2" (includes articles by E. Zabel and Y. Plessner), undated (Box 105)
    - Secondary sources for "6.3" (includes articles by L. Telser and others), undated (Box 105)
    - Secondary sources for "6" (includes articles by R. Rosenthal and others), undated (Box 105)
    - Sequential Games, undated (Box 123)
      Includes draft chapter 5 for unknown work
    - Sequential Optimization, undated (Box 105)
      Includes notes for chapter 4 of unknown work
    - Social Policy and Control..., undated (Box 105)
      Includes draft chapter 14 for unknown work
    - Strategic Audit, undated (Box 106)
      Includes material for chapter 14, including working papers and article, of unidentified work
    - Trade Practice Rules, undated (Box 106)
      Includes secondary sources for unidentified chapter 15
    - Unidentified draft: biography of Shubik, undated (Box 111)
    - Unidentified draft: culture and commerce, undated (Box 111)
    - Unidentified draft: Econometrica, undated (Box 111)
    - Unidentified manuscript: gaming, 1971 (Box 111)
    - Unidentified manuscript: latex economics, 1997 (Box 111)
      Includes paper and related correspondence
    - Urban Systems Gaming, undated (Box 106)
      Includes secondary sources for unidentified chapter 14
- Academia, 1961-2017; undated; 1
  This series includes files related to Shubik's teaching and work at Yale University.
  - Teaching, 1961-2006; undated; 1
    This subseries contains files for classes taught by Shubik, including syllabi, assignments, and readings.
    - Bidding Problem, 1985 (Box 126)
    - Center for Applied Mathematics, undated (Box 126)
    - City Polytechnic of Hong Kong, undated (Box 126)
    - Correspondence and course materials, Economics and Management of Culture, 1992 (Box 55)
    - Course evaluations, 1994 (Box 55)
    - Course evaluations, History of Money, 2001 (Box 55)
    - Course evaluations, Risk and Organization, 1987 (Box 54)
    - Course evaluations, Theory and History of Money and Financial Institutions, 1998 (Box 55)
    - Course materials, Defense Analysis Methodology, 1988 (Box 54)
    - Course materials, Derivatives and Financial Engineering, 1994 (Box 55)
    - Course materials, Financial Institutions, 1993 (Box 55)
    - Course materials, Games Theory in the Social Sciences, 1988 (Box 54)
    - Course materials, Gaming and its Applications, 1973-1975 (Box 54)
    - Course materials, Money and Financial Institutions, 1973 (Box 53)
    - Course materials, Risk and Organization, 1987 (Box 54)
    - Course materials, Risk and Organization, 1987 (Box 121)
    - Course materials, Securities Analysis and Portfolio Management, 1984-1985; 4 folders (Box 54)
    - Course materials, Seminar of Industrial Structure and Market Behavior, 1969-1970 (Box 54)
    - Course materials, Strategic Planning, Modeling and Economics, 1981 (Box 54)
    - Course materials, The Management and Economics of Culture, 1990 (Box 54)
    - Course materials, The Management and Economics of Culture, 1991 (Box 54)
    - Course materials, Theory of Money and Financial Institutions, 1991 (Box 54)
    - Course, Gaming and its Applications, 1974-1975 (Box 54)
    - Course, Material Money and Financial Institutions, 1976 (Box 54)
    - Course, Material Money and Financial Institutions, 1976 (Box 54)
    - Econ 451: Financial Institutions, 1992; 2005; 3 folders (Box 128)
      Includes lecture notes, readings, and other teaching materials
    - Evaluations, Derivatives and Financial Engineering, 1994 (Box 55)
    - Game Theory, undated (Box 129)
      Includes classroom exercises
    - Game Theory course materials, 1977 (Box 121)
    - Game Theory in the Social Sciences, 1991; 2 folders (Box 129)
      Includes syllabi, notes, and other teaching materials
    - International Security Studies and Arms Control at Yale University, 1986-1995 (Box 54)
    - Lecture notes, Money and Financial Institutions, with Whitman, M.S., 1972; 3 folders (Box 53)
    - Lecture notes, On Modeling in Political Economy, 1981 (Box 54)
    - Lecture notes, Paris, 1977-1978 (Box 121)
    - Lecture series notes, 1961; 2 folders (Box 53)
    - Lectures in microeconomics, University of Chile, 1965 (Box 53)
      Contents in Spanish
    - List of participants in microeconomics lecture, 1971-1972 (Box 53)
    - Management and Economics of Cultural Institutions, 1992; 2003; 2 folders (Box 129)
      Includes syllabi, readings, and other teaching materials
    - Management Simulation, 1972 (Box 129)
      Includes materials for a simulation exercise for management courses
    - Miscellaneous syllabi and lectures, 1961-2003 (Box 121)
    - On Matching Book: A Problem in Banking and Corporate Finance, undated (Box 126)
    - PhD thesis readings, 1960s-1970s (Box 53)
    - Seminar materials, Theory and History of Money and Financial Institutions, 1987-1988 (Box 54)
    - Seminar: The Theory of Money, 2004 (Box 129)
      Includes flyer
    - Seminar: Theory of Money and Financial Institutions, 1987; 1989; 2 folders (Box 129)
      Includes syllabi, assignments, and notes
    - Seminars and other materials, Chile, 1965 (Box 53)
    - Teaching list, Yale University Economics Department, 1994 (Box 55)
    - Teaching schedule, Shubik, 1998 (Box 55)
    - Theory and History of Money and Financial Institutions, 1998 (Box 129)
      Includes handouts
    - Thesis abstract, Sahi, Siddhartha, undated (Box 55)
    - Unidentified Teaching Materials, 1985; 2006; undated (Box 129)
    - Young Presidents' Organization course information, 1968 (Box 121)
  - Yale University, 1965-2017; undated; 2
    Includes files related to Shubik's departmental work, committee service, and contributions to programs outside of economics at Yale University.
    - Annual research report of M. Shubik, Yale University, 2003-2004 (Box 52)
    - Annual research reports of M. Shubik, Yale University, 1997-2002 (Box 52)
    - Annual research reports, Yale University, 1989-1999 (Box 50)
    - Barry O'Neill, 1998 (Box 51)
    - Dean, Yale College, 2006 (Box 126)
    - Defense Economics and Strategic Methodology, research at Yale University, 1980s-1990s (Box 51)
    - Defense Economics at Yale, proposals, correspondence, paper drafts, 1990s (Box 51)
    - Department of Operations Research, Yale, 1992-1995 (Box 126)
    - Dissertations, 1972 (Box 129)
    - Economic Impact of Terrorism, Yale Newsletter, 2002 (Box 52)
    - Games within the Games, Poli Sci Talk, undated (Box 129)
      Includes notes for talk given political science audience
    - Gaming Correspondence-General (related to Gaming Lab), 1965-1973 (Box 129)
    - Gaming Newsletter: Requests for Game, 1971-1972 (Box 129)
    - International Security Program at Yale University, grant proposals etc., 1977-1988; 3 folders (Box 50)
    - International Security Program, (annual report), 1992-1993 (Box 51)
    - Interview for Yale SOM History Project, 2017 (Box 129)
      Includes correspondence related to interview for Yale School of Management
    - Letters of recommendation, 2001 (Box 52)
    - Office of the Provost Yale University, 1995 (Box 126)
    - Provost, Defense, (ISAC Program at Yale), 1989-1990 (Box 50)
    - Recommendation letters, 1970s (Box 40)
    - Recommendation letters, 1977-1978 (Box 40)
    - Recommendation letters, 1980-1990 (Box 40)
    - Recommendation letters, 1989 (Box 40)
    - Recommendation letters, 1990-1991 (Box 40)
    - Recommendation Letters, 2007 (Box 126)
    - Recommendation letters, forms, 1970-1977 (Box 40)
    - Recommendations, undated (Box 52)
    - Sardine as Metaphor, Yale Newsletter, 2002 (Box 52)
    - Shubik's appointment for Knox Professorship at Yale University, 1975 (Box 48)
      Includes copy of newspaper announcement
- Personal, 1938-2012; undated; 1
  Contains biographical materials and other personal documents.
  - Acceptance letter appointing Shubik as adjunct research professor of operations research, undated (Box 50)
  - CV, 1960 (Box 129)
  - Desirable attributes of a University President, undated (Box 46)
  - Extract from the New Yorker, Three Procedures to the Stable Marriage Problem, November 9, 1974 (Box 46)
  - Frederick W. Lanchester Prize, 1983 (Box 49)
    Includes award certificate
  - From Bosnia to World Crisis, notes by Dujarric, Robert, 1995 (Box 46)
  - Guggenheim/Thomas Krens, 2009-2012 (Box 125)
  - Interview on the history of game theory, 1992 (Box 126)
    Interview conducted by Robert Leonard on Shubik's work on the core and other aspects of game theory
  - Interview with Andrew Marshall, The Marshall Plan, 2002 (Box 46)
  - Invitation to exhibition of Paintings by Baumol, 1957 (Box 46)
  - Job Offers, 1979 (Box 129)
    Includes correspondence related to job offers
  - Koopman Prize, 1995 (Box 51)
    Notification of receipt of award named in honor of Bernard Koopman
  - Lanchester Prize Awards, 1984 (Box 46)
  - Legal cases, Shubik v. Empire, Inc., v. Silverman, 1983 (Box 49)